Department of Special Collections, Hesburgh Libraries of Notre Dame
American Colonial Currency Collection
- Massachusetts Currency October 16, 1778Boston, MassachusettsMassachusettsOctober 16, 1778, MA 10/16/78; Paul Revere and Thomas Fleet;
  An emission of ฃ8,000 in legal tender bills of credit payable in lawful money from the state treasury by October 18, 1784. Issued to replace lower denomination notes emitted before October 18, 1776 (i.e. emissions of August 18th and December 7, 1775 and several small denominations of June 18th and October 18, 1776 and earlier), which according to the act passed on October 13, 1778, "suffers much from great numbers of them being much torn and otherwise defaced." Paul Revere's copper plates for the front side of the bills in the October 18, 1776 emission were redated and used for this issue. Apparently he printed the face of these notes. Also, Nathaniel Hurd's cast cuts of a pine tree made for the back side of the October 1776 issue were reused. However since the back of this issue was printed by Thomas Fleet (the earlier issue had been printed by John Gill) different type and border designs were used. The Massachusetts Historical Society has a restrike of the reverse plate that is autographed, "Presented by Mr. Thomas Fleet the printer 14 Septem 1799." The October 1778 act originally provided for the printing of ฃ28,000 of notes. However in an act passed on January 13, 1779 it was stated, "the copper plates are found insufficient for stamping the number of bills required." Clearly the used plates were worn out. Thus ฃ20,000 was to be forwarded to the next emission. This would be Revere's final currency project, the 1779 "Rising Sun" emission. Denominations issued in this October 16th emission were: 2d, 3d, 4d, 6d, 8d, 9d, 12d (1s), 1s6d, 2s, 3s, 4s and 4s6d.
  October 16, 1778- Codfish
  - Four Shillings2076 2076, 147; Signer: George Patridge.; Size: 73 x 65mm (front border design: 71 x 64mm; back border design: 62 x 54mm).
    The codfish is depicted at the top of the bill facing right (on some denominations it faces left). Also at the top is the date 1778, reworked on the plate which originally had 1776. Also above the right column is the date October 16, reworked from the original October 18. The scroll on the left column reads downward while that on the right colum reads upward. The imposition of Thomas Fleet's pine tree cut on the back is slightly off center with respect to the front; in our example it slightly crooked and is shifted approximately 8mm up and 10mm to the right.
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 lot 470. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Massachusetts Currency 1779Boston, MassachusettsMassachusetts1779, MA 1779; Paul Revere and Thomas Fleet;
  An emission of ฃ20,000 in bills of credit as part of the previous issue of October 16, 1778 but payable by December 1, 1782. The front of these bills was made from a newly created plate by Paul Revere depicting the sun rising. On each denomination the scene and borders are slightly different. Apparently Revere printed only the front of the bills. The back was typset by Thomas Fleet in Boston reusing the cast cuts of the pine tree previously used for the October 18, 1776 and October 16, 1778 issues. Revere's original copper plate, with the front of all twelve denominations survives in the Massachusetts State Archives. The American Antiquarian Society and the Massachusetts Historical Society both have restrikes of the plate. The Historical Society also has a presentation proof copper plate of the printed back of all twelve denominations. On the back of the plate is written "Presented to Mr. Thomas Fleet the printer 14 Septem. 1799." Also, the Chamberlain Collection in the Boston Public Library has Revere's handwritten bill to the state for ฃ713 6s8d for the engraving and printing of this issue. On this and the previous issues by Paul Revere see: Clarence S. Brigham, Paul Revere's Engravings, Atheneum: New York, 1969, pp. 213-241.
  1779- Rising Sun
  - Five Shillings6207 6207, 151; Signers: Richard Cranch.; Size: not available
    The rising sun differs on each denomination, here the sun has a face and rises over the left side of a hill. Image of the back of this bill is not available.
    Courtesy of Early American Numismatic Auctions, Inc. Images used with permission from their on-line auction catalog for the auction of April 20, 1996, lot 472
  - One Shilling2972 2972, 148; Signer: Jonathon Brown.; Size: 76 x 64mm (front border design: 73 x 60mm; back border design: 60 x 49mm).
    The rising sun differs on each denomination; this is the only illustration with a pine tree on the hill. The border design also difers by denomination.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EAHA mail bid auction of May 23, 1998, lot 379, where it was graded choice extremely fine.
  - Four Shillings6492 6492, 149; Signer: Richard Cranch.; Size: 74 x 63mm (front border design: 72 x 60mm; back border design: 60 x 49mm).
    The rising sun differs on each denomination; here it comes over the left side of a hill. Imposition of Thomas Fleet's pine tree cut on the back is slightly off center with respect to the front; in our example it is shifted approximately 3mm to the right.
    EANA mail bid auction 12/2/95 lot 451. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Four Shillings, Four Pence2701 2701, 150; Signers: Jonathon Brown.; Size: 76 x 64mm (front border design: 73 x 61mm; back border design: 62 x 49mm).
    The rising sun differs on each denomination; here it comes over the right side of a hill. Imposition of Thomas Fleet's pine tree cut on the back is slightly off-center with respect to the front; in this example it is shifted approximately 1.5mm to the left.
    EANA mail bid auction 12/2/95 lot 452. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Five Shillings, Four Pence2489 2489, 152; Signers: Jonathon Brown.; Size: 77 x 65mm (front border design: 72 x 60mm; back border design: 63 x 49mm).
    The rising sun differs on each denomination, here the sun has a face and rises directly over the peak of a hill. Imposition of Thomas Fleet's pine tree cut on the back is slightly off center with respect to the front; in this example it is shifted approximately 1.0mm to the left.
    EANA mail bid auction 12/2/95 lot 453. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Massachusetts Currency May 5, 1780Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaMassachusettsMay 5, 1780, MA 05/05/80; David Hall and William Sellers;
  An emission of ฃ394,000 ($1,313,333) in legal tender bills of credit payable in Spanish milled dollars with 5% interest by December 31, 1786. This issue was authorized pursuant to the Continental Congress Resolution of March 18, 1780. Printed by Hall and Sellers in Philadelphia using paper watermarked "United States." The front was printed in black with border cuts by Henry Dawkins. The back was printed in black and red with border cuts and emblems from the Continental Currency issue of January 14, 1779. The cuts surrounding the emblem are by Dawkins. Notes are sometimes surcharged in red "Interest paid one year" and usually hole canceled upon redemption. There are two signatures on the front and a guaranty signature on the back. Denominations issued were: $1, $2, $3, $4, $5, $7, $8 and $20.
  - Two Dollars13947 13947, 153; Signers: Thomas Dawes, Loammi Baldwin (front); Thomas Walley (back, guaranty signature).; Size: 72 x 92mm (front border design: 69 x 89mm; back border design: 69 x 89mm).
    Printed in red and black inks. The emblem on the back shows grain being threshed with a flail with the motto: "Tribulatio ditat." (It is enriched by affliction). The paper is watermarked "UNITED STATES." Surcharge stamped in red ink on front: "Interest Paid one Year."
    Robert H. Gore, Jr. Collection in Numismatics.
  - One Dollar2044 2044, 154; Signers: Richard Cranch, Samuel Henshaw (front); Peter Boyer (back, guaranty signature).; Size: 72 x 92mm (front border design: 69 x 89mm; back border design: 69 x 89mm).
    Printed in red and black inks. The emblem on the back depicts a bowl containing weights sitting on top of an acanthus bush with the motto: "Depressa resurgit" (Having been pressed down it rises up again). The paper is watermarked "UNITED STATES." Surcharge stamped in red ink on front: "Interest Paid one Year."
  - Three Dollars7664 7664, 155; Signers: Thomas Dawes, Richard Cranch (front); Thomas Walley (back, guaranty signature).; Size: 72 x 94mm (front border design: 69 x 89mm; back border design: 69 x 89mm).
    Printed in red and black inks. The emblem on the back shows an eagle and an heron fighting with the motto: "Exitus in dubio" (The outcome is in doubt). The paper is watermarked "UNITED STATES"; surcharge stamped in red ink on front: "Interest Paid one Year."
  - Four Dollars10853 10853, 156; Signers: Ebenezer Wales, Richard Cranch (front); Peter Boyer (back, guaranty signature).; Size: 71 x 90mm (front border design: 70 x 89mm; back border design: 69 x 90mm; long dimension of back border slightly cut off).
    Printed in red and black inks. The emblem on the back shows a wild boar charging into a spear with the motto: "Aut mors aut vita decora" (Either death or an honorable life). The paper is watermarked "UNITED STATES"; surcharge stamped in red ink on front: "Interest Paid one Year."
  - Four Dollars6692 6692, 157; Signers: Thomas Dawes, Richard Cranch (front); Thomas Walley (back, guaranty signature).; Size: 74 x 93mm (front border design: 70 x 89mm; back border design: 69 x 90mm; long dimension of back border slightly cut off).
    Printed in red and black inks. The emblem on the back shows a wild boar charging into a spear with the motto: "Aut mors aut vita decora" (Either death or an honorable life). The paper is watermarked "UNITED STATES." Hole Cancel; text partially missing from front read: "Thousand Seven/ in LIKE MONEY/ Annum, in the/ to an Act"; text partially missing from back read: "DECORA".
  - Five Dollars237224 237224, 158; Signers: Loammi Baldwin; Richard Cranch (front); Peter Boyer (back, guaranty signature).; Size: 71 x 92mm (front border design: 69 x 88mm; back border design: 69 x 91mm; long dimension of back border slightly cut off).
    Printed in red and black ink; numbered in red ink. The emblem on the back shows a hand in a thorn bush bleeding from pricks with the motto: "Sustine vel abstine" (With perseverance or with acquiesence). Paper contains blue fibers and mica flakes and is watermarked "UNITED STATES"; surcharge stamped in red ink on front: "Interest Paid one Year."
  - Seven Dollars12573 12573, 159; Signers: Thomas Dawes, Richard Cranch (front); Peter Boyer (back, guaranty signature).; Size: 71 x 98mm (front border design: 68 x 88mm; back border design: 69 x 92mm).
    Printed in red and black ink; numbered in red ink. The emblem on the back showsa storm at sea with the motto: "Serenabit" (It will clear up). Paper contains blue fibers and mica flakes and is watermarked "UNITED STATES"; surcharge stamped in red ink on front: "Interest Paid one Year."
  - Eight Dollars17791 17791, 160; Signers: Richard Cranch, Loammi Baldwin (front); Thomas Walley (back, guaranty signature).; Size: 72 x 95mm (front border design: 69 x 89mm; back border design: 69 x 92.5mm).
    Printed in red and black ink; numbered in red ink. The emblem on the back shows a harp with thirteen strings with the motto: "Majora minoribus consonant" (The larger are in harmony with the smaller). Paper contains blue fibers and mica flakes and is watermarked "UNITED STATES"; surcharge stamped in red ink on front: "Interest Paid one Year."
  - Twenty Dollars4953 4953, 161; Signers: Thomas Dawes, Ebenezer Wales (front); Thomas Walley (back, guaranty signature).; Size: 74 x 94mm (front border design: 70 x 89mm; back border design: 69 x 93mm).
    Printed in red and black ink; numbered in red ink. The emblem on the back shows a strong wind creating waves, with the motto: "Vi concitatae" (It assults with a violent force). Paper contains blue fibers and mica flakes and is watermarked "UNITED STATES"; surcharge stamped in red ink on front: "Interest Paid one Year."
- New Hampshire Currency April 3, 1742Boston, MassachusettsNew HampshireApril 3, 1742, NH 04/03/42; Thomas Johnston; Thomas Johnston
  An emission of ฃ4,720 in New Tenor legal tender bills of credit was authorized on April 3, 1742. The was the first New Hampshire issue of new tenor notes, which were valued at 6s8d per troy ounce of sterling silver (which was equal to 5s2d in British silver coinage). This was equal to four times the value of old tenor notes, therefore on the back of each note was the denomination in both old and new tenor; for example, 40s or ฃ2 new tenor was equal to ฃ8 in old tenor bills. An additional quantity of ฃ1,280 in notes were printed with this press run but were held in reserve until being issued under an act of September 28, 1743. The two plates for this emission were engraved in Boston by Thomas Johnston, who also printed the notes. The plates were then used for an emission authorized on April 3, 1742 for mortgage loans with the notes valued at 8s per troy ounce of sterling silver (but without changing the rate on the plates). This emission was approved by the Lords of Trade and Plantations in Britain on June 2, 1743 therefore the date 1743 was added to the plates just above the signature area, usually to the right of the center just below the frame around the text. Also the letter L was added to each engraving. The plates were then used for the February 1744/45 emission with the date of February 1744 added to the obverse of each note, somewhere below the central text, usually just below the central frame, toward the left margin. Additional quantities of notes were printed without any further redating of the plates for the following three issues: an emission of ฃ6,000 by an act of July 6, 1745; an emission of ฃ8,000 by an act of October 5, 1745 and finally a large emission of ฃ60,000 was authorized to finance an expedition into Canada by an act of July 12, 1746. During this period the value of sterling silver continued to rise so that by 1745 it was 8s9d per troy ounce. Notes from the February 1744/45 through the July 12, 1746 emissions cannot be distinguished. The dating 1744/45 refers to the situation that at that time the British celebrated the New Year in March so the date on the notes "February 1744" is converted to February 1745 using our current calendar. Denominations for the April 3, 1742 issue include: 6d, 1s, 2s6d, 6s, 7s6ds, 10s, 20s and 40s.
  - Forty Shillings (fragment), 162; Signers: missing.; Size: fragment 103 x 78mm.
    This is a torn fragment of the top one third of a note. The portion that remains is in very fine condition, indeed the front shows much of the top border, a section completley missing from the example plated by Newman (4th edition, p. 229). This fragment has been attributed to the original April 3, 1742 emission as there is no letter L on the note. The Newman plate of the 1743 redated variety has an L above the word Shillings at the top, the L is found on all denominates of reuses of the plate. Except for this added letter the specific emission of this note cannot be confirmed as the portion with the dating (and redating) is lost. With the exception of the added L the text visible on this fragment was the same as was printed on all emissions from April 3, 1742 to July 12, 1746. On the front the frame around the central text consists of acanthus leaves and flowers. From more complete examples the full text can be reconstructed: "PROVINCE OF NEW=HAMPSHIRE / 40.s Forty Shillings 40.s / This Bill of Forty Shillings due / to the Possessor thereof from ye province / of NEW-HAMPSHIRE shall be equal to Six Ounces of coin'd / Silver Troy Weight of Sterling Alloy, or / Gold Coin at ye Rate of Four Pounds / Eighteen Shillings pr Ounce, and shall be / so accepted in all payments and in the / TREASURY. PORTSMOUTH Apr. 3d 1742 / By Order of ye GENERAL / COURT or ASSEMBLY." Note that the O and F in the top line are separated on either side of the shell. The back of this example has much of the cartouche remaining. The face at the top is more distinct that in the Newman plate. Within this frame is the the old and new tenor equivalency but with a large ink stain, the text reads "Eight / Pounds. / Old Tenor. / Forty / Shillings" [that is, 40s New Tenor].
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the R.M. Smythe Sixth Annual Chicago Paper Money Exposition 2/17-18/2000, Auction 196, lot 1018.
- New Hampshire Currency February 16, 1744/45Boston, MassachusettsNew HampshireFebruary 16, 1745, NH 02/16/44-45; Thomas Johnston; Thomas Johnston
  An emission of ฃ13,000 in New Tenor bills of credit was authorized on February 16, 1745 to pay for the military expedition against Louisburg. The two plates used to print the notes had originally been engraved in Boston for the New Hampshire emission of April 3, 1742. The plates were then used for an emission approved in Britain on June 2, 1743; for that emission the date 1743 was added to the plates just above the signature area, usually to the right of the center just below the frame around the text. The plates were then used for the February 1744/45 emission with the date of February 1744 added to the obverse of each note, somewhere below the central text, usually just below the central frame, toward the left margin. Additonal quantities of notes were printed without any further redating of the plates for the follwoing three issues: an emission of ฃ6,000 by an act of July 6, 1745; an emission of ฃ8,000 by an act of October 5, 1745 and finally a large emission of ฃ60,000 was authorized to finance an expedition into Canada by an act of July 12, 1746. Notes from the February 1744/45 through the July 12, 1746 emissions cannot be distinguished. The dating 1744/45 refers to the situation that at that time the British celebrated the New Year in March so the date on the notes "February 1744" is converted to February 1745 using our current calendar. In the 1744/45 - 1746 emissions the backs of the four lower denomination notes were blank while the four higher denominations contained a scrollwork frame (called a cartouche) with the denomination printed in both the old tenor value as well as the new tenor equivalent value. At the time the plates were first engraved in 1742 the exchange was 4s old tenor for 1s new tenor. Denominations for this issue include: 6d, 1s, 2s6d, 6s, 7s6ds, 10s, 20s and 40s.
  February 1744/45
  - Twenty Shillings372 372, 163; Signers: George Jaffrey, Joseph Sherburne (in red ink), Eleazer Russell.; Size: 99 x 141mm.
    Numbering and first signature somewhat faded. This note is considered to be a contemporary counterfeit. The frame around the central text consists of acanthus leaves with the bottom portion consisting of the area for the serial number and the provincial seal, which displays a pine tree and the motto PROVINCE OF NEW HAMPSHIRE. On the 20s denomination the February 1744 date was added in the seal as Feby 1744. Just below the seal and slightly to the right the previous redating of the plate for the 1743 emission is evident. At the bottom is the British coat of arms to the left and to the right are the signatures of three members from the committee of twenty five signers. The back of this example has been reinforced with brown paper completely obscuring the printed text, originally the back of the note had the old and new tenor equivalency printed on it. Based on the Forty shilling example in Newman the back would have read: "Four / Pounds. / Old Tenor. / Twenty / Shillings" [that is, 20s New Tenor].
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the R.M. Smythe Fourth Annual Strasburg Paper Money Show 1/17/99, Auction 191, lot 1015 where it was mislabelled as Rhode Island.
- New Hampshire August 24, 1775Portsmouth, New HampshireNew HampshireAugust 24, 1775, NH 08.24.75; Daniel Fowle and Robert Fowle;
  An emission of ฃ8,000 in indented treasury bills of credit payable in lawful money with 6% interest over a period of three different due dates. One third were due on December 20, 1776, another third on December 20, 1777 and the final portion were due on December 20, 1778. The interest was revoked by the legislature on August 22, 1775. The bills were printed in typeset with ornamental borders on thin laid paper by Daniel and Robert Fowle in Portsmouth. Numbered in red with one signer in red and another in brown or black. Denominations for this issue include: 5s, 10s, 15s, 30s and ฃ3.
  - 3 pounds183 183, 164; Signers: Nicholas Gilman (in red ink), E. Thompson.; Size: 68 x 127mm (front border design: 66 x 120mm (including two rows of typeset at indent design); back blank).
    Numbering and one signature in red ink; the other signature in a faded brown ink. This indented note is from the group due payable on december 20, 1777. There are some tears and tape on the back. The back has a contemporary annotation of "8. 10 ." probably referring to shillings and pence. This note has a lightly annotated back.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 1/17/98, lot 326.
- New Hampshire Currency November 3, 1775 Portsmouth, New HampshireNew HampshireNovember 3, 1775, NH 11/03/75; Daniel Fowle;
  An emission of ฃ20,000 in indented treasury bills of credit payable in lawful money over a period of four different due dates ending on December 20, 1782. The bills were printed in typeset with ornamental borders on laid paper by Daniel Fowle in Portsmouth. In 1774 Daniel had ended his printing partnership with his nephew Robert Fowle, who was a Tory sympathizer. Together they had published the New Hampshire Gazette. Robert was arrested on April 5, 1777 for making counterfeits of the November 3, 1775 emission, using the same type as the originals (presumably the type had been divided when the partnership dissolved). Because of the counterfeits, on June 17, 1777 the House of Representatives of New Hampshire recalled all 1775 emissions. The four highest denominations are larger than the others. Numbered in red with one signer in red and another in black. Denominations for this issue include: 6d, 9d, 1s6d, 1s9d, 2s6d, 3s, 5s, 10s, 15s, 30s and 40s.
  - Forty Shillings2667 2667, 165; Signers: Nicholas Gilman (in red ink), Sam Hobart.; Size: 73 x 126mm (front border design: 64 x 117mm (excluding indented design); back blank).
    Numbering and first signature in red ink; second signature in black. There are two counterfeits of the 40s note, one with a 1779 due date and the other with a 1782 due date. This bill is of the later type. The counterfeit can be spotted because the period following the word "hereof" is located below the letter 'e' in the word "payments" from the line above, while in the original it is below the letter 'n'. The back is blank.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 1/13/96, lot 381.
- New Hampshire June 28, 1776Portsmouth, New HampshireNew HampshireJune 28, 1776, NH 06/28/76; Daniel Fowle;
  An emission of ฃ3,400 in legal tender treasury bills of credit payable on either January 26, 1787 or January 26, 1788. These are small typeset bills with border designs probably printed by Daniel Fowle of Portsmouth. Denominations for this issue include: 3d, 4d, 5d, 7d, 8d, 10d, 1s, 15d, 2s and 4s.
  - Four Shillings, 166; Signers: [faded]; Size: 47 x 71mm (front border design: 46 x 68mm; back blank).
    There are two due date varieties for this note: January 26, 1787 or January 26, 1788. Our example is of the second type. The back is blank.